Edward A. Wilson Papers
Edward A. Wilson Papers
1915-1963
Wilson, Edward A. (Edward Arthur), 1886-1970.
2.5 linear ft.
Spanning 1915 to 1963, the Edward A. Wilson Papers comprises biographical material, correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the Scottish-born illustrator, lithographer, and painter (1886-1970). The collection illuminates Wilson's artistic career, which ranged from book and magazine illustration to the design of advertisements, bookplates, magazine covers, postage stamps, and war posters.
149592
Biographical History
Edward Arthur Wilson (1886-1970) was a Scottish-born illustrator, lithographer, and painter.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1915 to 1963, the Edward A. Wilson Papers comprises biographical material, correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia. The collection illuminates Wilson's artistic career, which ranged from book and magazine illustration to the design of advertisements, bookplates, magazine covers, postage stamps, and war posters.
Correspondence-subject files consists primarily of incoming letters, as well as other documents relating to artwork. Among the correspondents are fellow artists (Charles Dexter Allen, C. B. Falls, Fred Freeman, Charles Dana Gibson, Marston Dean Hodgin, Joseph Pennell, Ray Prohaska, William Arthur Smith, Harve Stein); authors (David Bland, Theodore Bolton, Eugene Burdick, Earnest Elmo Calkins, Ashley Havinden, William A. Kittredge, George L. Moses, Harlan Ware); collector Wilbur Macey Stone; designers (Edwin Eberman, Bruce Rogers); editor Frank Shay; and publishers (Bennett Cerf, Storer B. Lunt, George Macy). Organizational correspondence includes art associations (American Institute of Graphic Arts, Boston Printmakers, Guild of Free Lance Artists, Print Club); art galleries and museums (Bezalel National Museum, San Joaquin Pioneer Museum and Haggin Art Galleries); clients (American Artists Group, Dutch Treat Year Book, Cadillac Motor Car Company, Cargoes, Forum, Life, John Morell & Co., Peck & Peck, Reader's Digest, Salmagundi Club); an educational institution (Rhode Island School of Design); and publishing houses (R. R. Donnelley & Sons Company, Doubleday, Doran and Company, Doubleday, Page & Co., Grosset & Dunlap, Houghton Mifflin Company, Rand McNally & Company, Random House, John C. Winston Company).
Artwork encompasses advertisements, book illustration, bookplates (5), magazine cover design and illustration, postage stamp design (2), and war poster art (4), as well as miscellaneous reproductions and one original woodcut. Advertisements are arranged by client name while book and magazine illustration and design work are organized under title. Postage stamps, war poster art, and miscellaneous reproductions are arranged chronologically. Articles and Speeches, both typescript and printed, constitute Writings.
Memorabilia includes photographs and printed material. Images of Wilson in his studio and with ship models as well as prints of two Wilson portraits by Jerry Farnsworth and William Oberhardt constitute Photographs. Printed material comprises articles and reviews (1922-1958), newspaper clippings (1915-1963), exhibition catalogs and invitations (1930-1954), one exhibition poster, and book publicity (1924-1942).
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence-subject files are arranged alphabetically. Artwork, writings and memorabilia are arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Allen, Charles Dexter, 1865-1926.; Bennett, Paul A., 1897-1966.; Bland, David (David Farrant); Bolton, Theodore, 1889-1973.; Burdick, Eugene.; Calkins, Earnest Elmo, 1868-1964.; Cerf, Bennett, 1898-1971.; Eberman, Edwin.; Falls, C. B. (Charles Buckles), 1874-1960.; Freeman, Fred, 1906-1988.; Gibson, Charles Dana, 1867-1944.; Havinden, Ashley.; Heintzelman, Arthur William, 1891-1965.; Kittredge, William.; Macy, George.; Maule, Harry E. (Harry Edward), 1886-; Moses, George L.; Pennell, Joseph, 1857-1926.; Prohaska, Ray.; Rogers, Bruce, 1870-1957.; Rowland, Earl.; Shay, Frank, 1888-1954.; Stein, Harvé, 1904-1996.; Stone, Wilbur Macey.; Ware, Harlan.; Whitehill, Walter Muir, 1905-1978.; Wilson, Edward A. (Edward Arthur), 1886-1970.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Commercial art.; Commercial artists -- United States.; Illustration of books -- United States -- 20th century.; Illustrators -- United States.; Lithographers -- United States.; Magazine covers.; Magazine illustration -- 20th century.; Marine art, American.; Marine artists -- United States.; Painters -- United States.; Printmakers -- United States.; Scottish Americans.; Advertisements.; Articles.; Book illustrations.; Bookplates.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Artists.; Illustrators.; Lithographers.; Painters.; Printmakers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Allen, Charles Dexter, 1925 (Box 1)
  - American Artists Group Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1936-1940 (Box 1)
  - American Institute of Graphic Arts (New York, N.Y.), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Bennett, Paul A., 1955 (Box 1)
  - Bezalel National Museum (Jerusalem, Israel), 1954 (Box 1)
  - Bland, David, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Bolton, Theodore, See Century Association
  - Boston Printmakers, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Boston Public Library, 1951-1954 (Box 1)
  - Burdick, Eugene, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Cadillac Motor Car Company (Detroit, Mich.), 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - Calkins, Earnest Elmo, 1925; 1955,; 1962 (Box 1)
  - Cargoes (Summit, N.J.), 1931 (Box 1)
  - Century Association (New York, N.Y.), 1956 (Box 1)
  - Cerf, Bennett, See Random House, Inc.
  - R. R. Donnelley & Sons Company (Chicago, Ill.), 1930-1932 (Box 1)
  - Doubleday, Doran and Company (Garden City, N.Y.), 1928-1938 (Box 1)
  - Doubleday, Page & Co. (Garden City, N.Y.), 1925; 1927 (Box 1)
  - Dutch Treat Year Book, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Eberman, Edwin, 1953; 1954 (Box 1)
  - Falls, C. B., See Guild of Free Lance Artists
  - Forum (New York, N.Y.), 1929 (Box 1)
  - Franklin Bookshop (Philadelphia, Pa.), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Freeman, Fred, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Gibson, Charles Dana, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Grosset & Dunlap Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - Guild of Free Lance Artists (New York, N.Y.), 1921 (Box 1)
  - Havinden, Ashley, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Heintzelman, Arthur William, See Boston Public Library
  - Heritage Press (New York, N.Y.), See Macy, George
  - Hodgin, Marston Dean, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Houghton Mifflin Company (New York, N.Y.), 1958 (Box 1)
  - Ketterlinus Lithographic Manufacturing Co. (Philadelphia, Pa.), 1937 (Box 1)
  - Kittredge, William A., See R. R. Donnelley & Sons Company
  - Kleppner Company (New York, N.Y.), 1953 (Box 1)
  - Life (New York, N.Y.), 1955; undated (Box 1)
  - Limited Editions Club (New York, N.Y.), See Macy, George
  - Lunt, Storer B., 1955 (Box 1)
  - Macy, George, 1929-1959 (Box 1)
  - George Macy Companies, Inc. (New York, N.Y.), See Macy, George
  - Macy, Helen, See Macy, George
  - Maule, Harry E., See Doubleday, Doran and Company
  - John Morrell & Co. (Ottumwa, Iowa), 1937 (Box 1)
  - Moses, George L., 1963 (Box 1)
  - New York Public Library, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Peck & Peck (New York, N.Y.), 1932 (Box 1)
  - Pennell, Joseph, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Pictorial Review (New York, N.Y.), See Macy, George
  - Print Club (Philadelphia, Pa.), 1936 (Box 1)
  - Prohaska, Ray, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Rand McNally & Company (Chicago, Ill.), 1954; 1956 (Box 1)
  - Random House, Inc., 1951 (Box 1)
  - Reader's Digest, 1953-1961; undated (Box 1)
  - Rhode Island School of Design, 1953-1954; undated (Box 1)
  - Rogers, Bruce, 1927; 1954-1957 (Box 1)
  - Rowland, Earl, See San Joaquin Pioneer Museum and Haggin Art Galleries
  - Salmagundi Club (New York, N.Y.), 1952 (Box 1)
  - San Joaquin Pioneer Museum and Haggin Art Galleries (Stockton, Calif.), 1959 (Box 1)
  - Shay, Frank, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Smith, William Arthur, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Stein, Harve, 1955 (Box 1)
    See also Rhode Island School of Design
  - Stone, Wilbur Macey, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Ware, Harlan, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Whitehill, Walter Muir, 1951 (Box 1)
  - John C. Winston Company (Philadelphia, Pa.), 1955 (Box 1)
  - A-Z (Box 1)
  - Unidentified (Box 1)
- Artwork (Box 2)
  - Advertisements, A-Z by company, includes 4 original signed lithographs (Oversize 1)
  - Book illustration
    - Deep Sea Chanties, reproductions (Box 2)
    - Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde, worksheets, proofs; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Full and By, reproductions (Box 2)
    - Green Mansions, original drawings, proofs; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Iron Men and Wooden Ships, reproductions (Box 3)
    - Ivanhoe, worksheets, proofs; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Longfellow, proofs (Box 3)
    - The Mysterious Island, proofs (Box 3)
    - Ranging the Maine Coast, original signed lithograph -"Maine Lobsterman" (Box 3)
    - The Seven Voyages of Sinbad the Sailor, proofs (Box 3)
    - Twenty Thousand Leagues Under the Sea, sketches, worksheets; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Westward Ho!, worksheets, proofs; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Bookplates. A-Z (by name of person or organization), 5 items (Box 3)
  - Magazine cover design and illustration, A-Z (by title of magazine) (Box 3)
  - Postage stamp design, undated; 2 items (Box 3)
  - War poster art, 1943; 1944,; undated; 4 items (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Other reproductions, 1925; 1926,; undated (Box 3)
    - Woodcut (original), undated (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Articles, speeches, 1957; 1963,; undated (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs
    - Portraits of Wilson, drawn by William Oberhardt, painted by Jerry Farnsworth, undated; 2 items (Box 4)
    - Wilson, Edward A., undated (Box 4)
  - Printed material
    - Articles, reviews, 1922-1958; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1915-1963; undated (Box 4)
    - Exhibition catalogs, 1930-1954; undated (Box 4)
    - Exhibition invitations, receipts, 1954; undated (Box 4)
    - Exhibition poster, undated (Box 4)
    - Publicity (book), 1924-1942; undated (Box 4)